A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs, Office Files of Joseph E. Slater FA619
Rockefeller Archive Center
Program differentiation began in the Gaither era. When he began in 1953, he introduced the following programs, with international work under nearly all of them: International Programs, Public Affairs Programs, Program in Economic Development and Administration [mainly U.S. based], Education Program, The TV-Radio Workshop, and Behavioral Sciences Program. In 1954, the Foundation gave prominence to the international work explicitly through changing the program names and separating international affairs and overseas development. The 1954 program names were: The Advancement of Education, Education for Democracy, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas, Economic Development and Administration, the Behavioral Sciences, and Overseas Development. In 1955, Increasing Knowledge of Foreign Areas became Increasing International Understanding. In 1956, the last year of the Gaither presidency, the program roster read: Education in the United States, The Behavioral Sciences, Public Affairs, Hospital Aid (only in the U.S.), Economic Development and Administration, International Understanding, and Overseas Development. Names changed but the program focus often remained the same.
President Heald maintained the areas of international interest of Hoffman and Gaither. The International Affairs program housed the programs based in the United States, Europe and Japan, with a few activities linking American and developing countries institutions. The Overseas Training and Research Program took over the efforts to increase American understanding of international issues. From 1957-1959, an International Legal Studies program, run from New York, helped build law programs in developing countries. Starting in 1959, the Overseas Development program comprised all the regional and country offices. In fiscal year 1964, Heald convinced the trustees to add a new focus on population, with grants both in the United States and overseas.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 2. Period Summary - The Expansion Era 1950-1965
With the ever-increasing budget and trustee willingness to invade capital, presidents Hoffman, Gaither and Heald oversaw vast growth in the Foundation's international activities in the United States, other developed countries and developing countries. Activities crossed disciplines, institutions, and national boundaries, although few crossed intra-foundation boundaries. Under the three presidents, Foundation staff in various domestic and international offices from New York interacted with the regional and country offices headed by representatives. Usually in this period, however, these offices in fact worked more closely with local governments than with New York staff, reinforcing the commitment to locally led social and economic development in less-developed countries.
The shared values of this early period reflected as much the continuing competition between the Communist and capitalist worlds as the concerns about maintaining peace. The Cold War provided the contextual continuity for grantmaking on the core themes of increasing American understanding of the rest of the world, building and strengthening connections not only with European and Asian democracies but also with Eastern European countries, the Soviet Union, China, and Cuba.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 3. Period Sketch - Transition and Restructuring 1966-1988
In the 1960s, the Ford Foundation Trustees began to rethink the role of the Foundation in the context of the era's dramatic political and cultural changes. For instance, the passage of the 1964 Civil Rights Act created a domestic policy context in which the Foundation could more deeply engage with issues of rights and social justice. Events overseas starting in the late 1960s would extend the rights agenda to international affairs and development operations at the Foundation -- all advanced by the leadership of McGeorge Bundy (president, 1966-1979).
McGeorge Bundy was appointed president in 1966, following a significant career in national security and academic administration. During World War II, he worked with the Army's intelligence division, and in the early post-war years was a political analyst at the Council on Foreign Relations. Even without a postgraduate degree, at the age of thirty -four he became dean of the Faculty of Arts and Science at Harvard University. In 1961, President Kennedy appointed Bundy to be Special Assistant to the President for National Security - a position he held for five years under both Kennedy and Johnson. Those significant years saw the Bay of Pigs invasion, the Cuban Missile Crisis, and the beginnings of the Vietnam War.
When Bundy arrived at the Foundation, he initiated a restructuring that modeled government departments rather than the academic ones President Henry Heald had established in the 1950s. At the same time, he had to contend with serious financial constraints due to Ford's overspending in the prior periods and to economic downturns in the global economy. The Board of Trustees mandated an annual spending of over $100 million.
These economic constraints meant that Foundation programs had to be more selective across the range of its programs. Nonetheless, international activities remained prominent with the new president and trustees. President Bundy and key trustees such Eugene Black (1960-1968, former head of the World Bank) and Robert S. McNamara (1968-1986, former U.S. Secretary of Defense and then head of the World Bank, 1968-1981) reflected a commitment to the international activities. Bundy also added to the board in 1972 the first trustee from a developing country, the Indonesian activist and scholar, Dr. Soedjakmoto, the former Ambassador to the United States from his country and then Special Adviser on Social and Cultural Affairs to the Chairman of Indonesia's National Development Planning Agency.
To create economies of scale, Bundy unified US-based international and overseas activities under one division: the International Division (using the name for the first time). That division comprised Resources for Development (area studies, languages, and exchanges), Population, International Relations, Planning and Evaluation, and the country programs. David Bell, an economist and the first administrator of the US Agency for International Development (1962-1966), was named vice president and served in that capacity until the end of Bundy presidency.
In 1966, Bundy terminated the long-standing internationally oriented but domestically based International Training and Research Program. Several large domestic programs -- including support of centers of international studies - were phased out in the 1970s. Instead, Ford launched under its international affairs efforts a focused but robust program in security and arms control. Over Bundy's tenure, the overseas offices were reduced from twenty in 1966 to twelve in 1979, when he retired.
The Foundation increasingly turned its attention to different set of international issues including human rights and working in repressive societies, such as South Africa. The military coups in Latin America during the late 1960s and early 1970s led the Foundation to initiate in 1976 a human rights program housed in Vice President Bell's office.
In 1979, Franklin Thomas was named president of the Ford Foundation (1979-1996). In contrast to Bundy's international and defense policy background, Franklin Thomas brought to the Ford Foundation his experience in law, housing, and community development. Prior to joining the Foundation, Thomas, a lawyer, was a Foundation trustee. He chaired the Rockefeller Foundation-funded Study Commission on U.S. Policy towards South Africa and led the Ford-funded Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation in New York from its beginning in 1966 until he left in 1979. Earlier, he had been deputy police commissioner of NYC.
In the first decade of Thomas' tenure, the international work was still framed using the post-war East-West dichotomy. Several trustees brought to the board active engagement in international issues: Donald F. McHenry (trustee over the period 1981-1993) had served as ambassador to the U.N. and was active in the anti-apartheid movement; and General Olusegun Obasanjo (trustee over the period 1987-1999) had been Nigerian head of state from 1976-1979, and was then president of the African leadership Forum. Along with McNamara and Soedjakmoto, Rodrigo Botero, an internationally renowned economist from Colombia and former Colombian Minister of Finance and Credit from 1974 to1976, remained on the board over the period 1978-1989.
During the early years of the Thomas presidency, the scope and strategies of the Foundation's activities were also influenced by economic and global pressures, leading to reduced assets and further financial stringencies. Thomas' board-mandated reductions resulted, for example, the firing of twenty senior staff at the same time. To achieve more effective and efficient programs, Thomas had a vision of Ford as one foundation, linking the domestic and overseas activities under new program themes: Urban Poverty, Rural Poverty and Resources, Human Rights and Social Justice, Governance and Public Policy, Education and Culture, and International Affairs.
The restructured Foundation comprised two programmatic divisions led by vice presidents: U.S. and International Affairs Programs (USIAP) headed by Susan Berresford; and Developing Countries Program (DCP), headed by William Carmichael. Berresford had been at the Foundation since 1970, coming from the U.S. Manpower Career Development Agency. She served in the National Affairs area, first as program assistant and then program officer (1972-1980), becoming head of women's programs in 1980. The main international efforts under USIAP were housed in Rural Poverty and Resources, Human Rights and Governance, and International Affairs. The other programs - Urban Poverty, Education and Culture, and Program-Related Investments - also addressed a scattering of international issues related to their main themes.
Carmichael had joined the Foundation in 1968 as Representative in Brazil. In July 1971, he was named Head of the Office of Latin America and the Caribbean, and in September of 1977, he became Head of the Middle East and Africa Office. The DCP program was responsible for all the Field Offices: Andean and the Southern Cone, Brazil, Mexico and Central America, Bangladesh, India, Southeast Asia, West Africa, Eastern and Southern Africa, and Middle East and North Africa.
When the Foundation initiated a Human Rights and Governance program (HR&G) in 1981, it was the first instance of a Ford program explicitly entitled "human rights," despite the fact that human rights grantmaking that had started officially in 1976. International Affairs remained separate from HR&G. In 1987, however, the Board conceptually linked three programs, creating a Trustee committee called Human Rights, Governance, and International Affairs, which existed until 1992. Operationally, however, the programs relating to these fields did not often work together.
International governance remained a commitment under Thomas. The Foundation, for example, had a long-established relationship with the United Nations: from 1951 until 1988, the United Nations received ninety grants from the Foundation (it received another 198 over the period 1989-2009).
In these early years of the Thomas presidency, dramatic changes were occurring in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. Under President Mikhail Gorbachev's leadership since 1985, the USSR was opening up to the international community, the rule of law in society was taking prominence there, and press freedoms were spreading. The foundation developed new programs in the region, drawing on the $60 million already spent to promote human rights and free expression and increase Western understanding of developments there.
Given the continuing economic constraints facing the Foundation and rising debt in developing countries, the Foundation shifted support under DCP to smaller scale community-based initiatives in the field offices. Thomas was also charged by the Board to increase the diversity of grantees, especially to favor populations "most affected" by the problems of concern to the Ford Foundation. The Foundation built on earlier efforts and sharpened its focus on women's issues throughout the world, including shifting the focus of the population program to women' reproductive health and child survival.
In the 1980s, Carmichael and others, with strong support from Thomas and the board, continued the 1970s' support of South African grantees for training large numbers of black lawyers and litigating sensitive cases in the South African legal system. Recognizing the multifaceted nature of discrimination in South Africa, the Foundation not only advanced the rule of law, but also strengthened civic organizations, women's groups, and educational institutions. Further, it supported a number of activist organizations in the United States that were energetically advocating US governmental sanctions against South Africa and for private disinvestment. The Foundation also played a role in shaping US policy on apartheid through the role Thomas played from 1985 to 1987 chairing the US Secretary of State's Advisory Committee on South Africa.
The Foundation's overseas staff also sought to improve the economic situation in poor, marginalized communities through targeted loan programs particularly to women head of households, beginning with the innovative work in Bangladesh of Professor Mohammed Yunus, the founder of the Grameen Bank. The results led the way to establish the field of microfinance with the aim of empowering women living in poverty conditions, such as through a microfinance network in Latin America starting 1980 and a global lending program for women starting in 1987.
Thomas encouraged staff to share results at worldwide meetings. During those meetings, Ford staff in the country offices and in New York tried to follow the mandate to work as "one foundation." The persistent challenge toward meeting that goal, however, was that initiatives emerging from the New York-based programs, or indeed any program developed in one country, were not always adaptable, relevant or acceptable in other countries or regions. It remained a challenge to develop a unified program, despite the commitment at the highest level of foundation leadership.
Biographical / Historical
Segment 3. Period Summary - Transition and Restructuring 1966-1988
During this era, the Foundation's earlier interest in business and the economy evolved into a commitment to improving conditions for people living on the margins of society. The Ford Foundation promoted advancements in women's rights around the globe and introduced micro-lending into grantmaking. At the same time, the economic issues that were shaping program strategies also affected the Foundation's assets. Severe cuts resulted in a significant restructuring of country programs and reduced budgets across all programs.
Even with the cuts in country offices, in the 1970s Ford grantees in developing countries received approximately 80% of the International Division budget. The remaining fifth went to Population, Development Studies, and International Affairs. Although representing a much smaller piece, the International Security and Arms Control program from 1973 was the Foundation's most concerted effort to make meaningful inroads in disarmament and nuclear issues - those challenges most directly linked to the Foundation's historic concern for peace. By 1979, the Ford Foundation was the biggest funder of arms control as a field, both in the U.S. and overseas.
- CHRONOLOGICAL FILES, 1957-1967; I
  Arrangement
  CHRONOLOGICAL FILES and the material within each fie, are arranged in reverse chronological order. The folder titles are also listed in reverse chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  SERIES I, CHRONOLOGICAL FILES (1957-1967), consists of 7.5linear feet of Slater's outgoing correspondence to persons outside the Foundation and to Foundation staff, his memoranda to the files, as well as copies and drafts of requests for grant action (RGAs). CHRONOLOGICAL FILES are a comprehensive documentation of Slater's activities while at the Foundation. The files covering the months September 1960 to August 1957 also contain some of Slater's incoming correspondence. Additional correspondence between Slater and many of the individuals in the latter group may be found in other series. CHRONOLOGICAL FILES also contain two folders of memoranda documenting Slater's May-June 1959 trip to Europe. These files are best used in conjunction with the additional memoranda in the corresponding TRIP NOTES (Series VI) file. There are no chronological files for the November 1961 to November 1960 period, during which time Slater was on a leave of absence.
  - 1967 November - April (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
  - 1967 March - 1966 September (Box 2, Folder 12-21)
  - 1966 August - January (Box 3, Folder 22-31)
  - 1965 December - April (Box 4, Folder 32-42)
  - 1965 March - 1964 November (Box 5, Folder 43-52)
  - 1964 October - April (Box 6, Folder 53-62)
  - 1964 March - 1963 August (Box 7, Folder 63-71)
  - 1963 July - January (Box 8, Folder 72-81)
  - 1962 December - February (Box 9, Folder 82-92)
  - 1962 January - 1961 December, 1960 October - June (Box 10, Folder 93-102)
  - 1960 May - June (Box 11, Folder 103-111)
  - 1959 December - May (European Trip May-June 1959) (Box 12, Folder 112-120)
  - 1959 June - 1958 October (Box 13, Folder 121-129)
  - 1958 September - April (Box 14, Folder 130-136)
  - 1958 March - 1957 August (Box 15, Folder 137-143)
- GEOGRAPHIC FILES, 1957-1967; II
  SERIES II, GEOGRAPHIC FILES (1957-1967), consists of 2.25 linear feet of correspondence, memoranda, notes, and drafts of reports. GEOGRAPHIC FILES are divided into three subseries: ASIA PACIFIC, EUROPE/ATLANTIC and LATIN AMERICA. Within each sub series the material is further divided into the following sections: countries, individuals, organizations, and topics. The organizations which are filed in each section are entered by name in the ORGANIZATION FILES (Series IV) folder listings with the appropriate cross reference to Series II. Other cross references are indicated in the folder listings. The GEOGRAHIC FILES are best used in conjunction with the TRIP NOTES (Series VI).
  GEOGRAPHIC FILES are comprised of three subseries: ASIA/PACIFIC, EUROPE/ATLANTIC, and LATIN AMERICA. They are arranged in alphabetical order. Within each subseries the sections are arranged in alphabetical order. The material within each folder is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - ASIA/PACIFIC, 1
    Related Materials
    See also: Trip Notes (Series VI), Asia/Pacific, 1963-67, and Subjects Files (Series V), Office of International Affairs.
    - Countries
      - Australia - correspondence, memoranda, 1967 February - 1965 April, 1964 November - 1961 January (Box 16, Folder 144-145)
        See also: 'Asia/Pacific, Education' for Australian National University.
      - China, 1967 October - 1962 February (Box 16, Folder 146)
        See also: Asia/Pacific, Individuals - Kenneth Young; Organization Files (Series IV), Council on Foreign Relations.
      - Hong Kong - correspondence, 1965 July - 1963 September (Box 16, Folder 147)
      - Hong Kong - memoranda, 1965 August - 1960 April (Box 16, Folder 148)
      - Japan - miscellaneous correspondence, memoranda, 1967 April - 1962 January (Box 16, Folder 149)
      - Japan - Herbert Passin memoranda, 1967 May - 1962 June (Box 16, Folder 150-151)
      - Korea, 1967 June - 1966 February (Box 16, Folder 152)
      - New Zealand, 1968 February - 1961 August (Box 16, Folder 153)
      - The Philippines, 1964 January (Box 16, Folder 154)
    - Individuals
      See also: 'Asia/Pacific ADELA'; 'Latin America, ADELA' for Jacob Javits. See also: 'Subjects Files (Series V), Office of International Affairs - General' for Charles McVicker. See also: 'Asia/Pacific, Japan; Korea' for Herbert Passin.
      - Kenneth Young, 1967 March - 1964 May (Box 16, Folder 155)
        See also: Subjects Files (Series V), Office of International Affairs - IA Program Review.
    - Organizations
      - ADELA Investment Company, 1967 October - 1966 July (Box 16, Folder 156)
        See also: Latin America, ADELA
      - Asian Broadcasting Union, 1966 June - May (Box 16, Folder 157)
    - Topics
      - Education - Australian National University, 1966 June - March (Box 16, Folder 158)
        See also: 'Asia/Pacific, Hong Kong' for Chinese University of Hong Kong.
  - EUROPE/ATLANTIC, 2
    See also: Trip Notes (Series VI), Europe, 1958-59; Subject Files (Series V), Office of International Affairs; Chronological Files (Series I).
    - Countries
      For Developing Countries see: 'Europe/Atlantic, Topics'. For France see: 'Meetings, U.S. French roundtable'. For Latin America see: 'Europe/Atlantic, developing countries'.
      - Austria, 1967 October - 1966 October (Box 17, Folder 159)
        See also: Trip Notes (Series VI), Shepard Stone trip notes - Europe 1957.
      - Berlin, 1965 December - 1962 January (Box 17, Folder 160)
        See also: Meeting Files (Series III), Berlin Advisory Group and Cultural Projects for Berlin.
      - Canada, 1966 January - 1964 April (Box 17, Folder 161)
      - Cyprus, 1962 November (Box 17, Folder 162)
      - Eastern Europe, 1967 April - 1959 November (Box 17, Folder 163)
        See also: 'Europe/Atlantic, Zbignew Brzezinski' - 1957 April'.
      - Germany, 1966 December - 1959 November (Box 17, Folder 164)
        See also: 'Europe/Atlantic, developing countries'.
      - Great Britain, 1966 March - 1959 May (Box 17, Folder 165)
      - Italy (Box 17, Folder 166)
      - The Netherlands, 1957 November - October (Box 17, Folder 167)
      - Spain, 1967 August (Box 17, Folder 168)
    - Individuals
      For Miriam Camps, see: Trip Notes (Series VI), Europe 1958-1959. For Walter Dowling, see: Organization Files (Series IV), The Atlantic Institute. For J.B. Duroselle, see: Europe/Atlantic, Developing countries: Latin America; and Trip Notes (Series VI), Europe 1958-1959. For Jacques Freymond, see: Europe/Atlantic, Economy: European Free Trade Area. For Raymond Goldsmith, see: Organization Files (Series IV), OECD. For Michel Gordey, see: Meeting Files (Series III), U.S.-French roundtable; and Organization Files (Series IV), International Broadcast Institute. For Max Kohnstamm, see: Organiztion Files (Series IV), The Atlantic Institute. For H. Philip Mettger, see: Europe/Atlantic, Young Leaders Project.
      - Brzezinski, Zbignew, 1967 March (Box 17, Folder 169)
      - Heaps, David, 1963 June - 1962 December (Box 17, Folder 170)
      - Huntley, James, 1967 January - 1963 July (Box 17, Folder 171-173)
        See also: Europe/Atlantic, Young Leaders Project; Meeting Files (Series III), U.S.-French roundtable; and Subject Files (Series V), Citizen Education on World Affairs.
      - Konz, Peider, 1966 February - 1965 July (Box 17, Folder 174)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1966 August - May 1957 (Box 17, Folder 175)
      - Moore, Ben T., 1965 May - 1962 February (Box 17, Folder 176)
      - Neumann, Robert, 1964 May (Box 17, Folder 177)
        See also: Meeting Files (Series III), U.S.-French roundtable.
      - Schatzel, J. Robert, 1967 February - 1962 April (Box 17, Folder 178)
        See also: Organization Files (Series IV), The Atlantic Institute; and Subject Files (Series V), Public Service.
    - Organizations